影片封装:哥本傻根
想要更多高清请加QQ:188295557
真是没有规矩,快走开
Behave yourself! Get away!
来来,吃西瓜
Come have some watermelon
你们两个真是太客气了
You are too polite.
应该到这里来一起吃饭的嘛
You should come and eat with us!
真的不客气,吃饱了
You're wat too kind. We've already eaten.
桂美呢
Where's Kuei-mei?
怎么不叫她一起来
Didn't you ask her to come?
对了,老大,老二,去叫表姨来
Get your auntie here.
说柴妈妈来了
Tell her Momma Chai is here.
妈妈叫你去的啦
Mom asked you to go.
你去啦！妈妈叫你去的啦
Go on.
- Mom asked you to go.
快去啊,快
Hurry!
表姨,妈妈说柴妈妈来了
Auntie, mom says Mrs. Chai is here
叫你快点去
She wants you to go.
去给你介绍男朋友啦
She wants to introduce a guy to you.
不要跑,当心摔倒
Don't run, you'll hurt yourself.
侯先生属什么的
Mr. Hou, what is your Chinese Zodiac?
属龙
Dragon.
那桂美呢
What about Kuei-mei?
我们桂美啊
Kuei-mei is...
桂美来了
Here's Kuie-mei.
桂美,来
Kuie-mei, come.
侯先生,府上是哪里
Mr. Hou, where is your hometown?
老侯跟我先生是同乡南京人
Same as my husband, Nanking.
南京啊
Nanking!
撒退的时候啊
During the retreat...
我们在那里住过一阵子
We stayed there for a while.
冬天啊,冻死人
It freezes you in winter.
夏天啊,比台北还热呢
In summer, it's hotter than Taiwan.
是啊
Yes... Yes...
喝茶,谢谢！
Have some tea.
- Thank you.
真是的,这一幌眼啊
We've lived here for more than 7 years.
在这里居然住了七,八年了
Well... in a glance...
当初啊,谁会想得到呢
Who knows?
总以为住住就回去了
We thought we were only staying
for a while...
是啊
That's right...
抽烟
Do you smoke?
不会,他烟酒都不会
No...he doesn't smoke or drink.
好,那好
Good.
他们在饭店做事啊
They work in a restaurant.
经理就是洋人
The manager is a foriegner
管得严,不准抽烟
He doesn't allow them to smoke.
连大蒜啊,也不能吃耶
They can't even eat garlic.
为什么
Why not?
怕把客人臭死啊
The smell might chase customers away.
那打牌吧
What about mahjongg?
有时候玩玩
Sometimes.
输赢不大
They bet little
偶尔打个小牌倒没有关系
It's fine to play a little.
不要像她,一天打到晚
Don't play every day, like her.
家里要是没有桂美帮着
Without Kuei-mei,
连烧饭都没人
there wouldn't be anybody to cook.
谁一天到晚打牌了
Who plays everyday?
见你的大头鬼
Nonesense!
桂美,好像不会打牌峨
Can Kui-mei play?
她不会
No, she doesn't
是啊,我们桂美啊
That's right! Our Kuie-mei...
可是一点坏毛病都没有
Doesn't have any bad habits.
那像我呀
Unlike me.
在他眼里啊
In his eyes
我是一点好处也没有
I am good for nothing
好了,好了
OK, OK.
你们不要吵了
Don't make a fuss.
桂美啊,实在是好乖哦
Kui-mei is really nice.
每天啊,都是忙东忙西的
She's busy all daylong.
那当然了
Of course.
这绿岛像一艘船
The island is like a boat,
在月夜里摇呀摇
swinging in the moon light.
姑娘呀
My lady
你也在我的心海里飘呀飘
you also swing in my mind.
让我的歌声
Let my voice
随那微风
pass with the wind.
揭开了你的窗帘
Open your curtain.
让我的衷情
Let my love
随那流水
float with the river
不断的向你倾诉
to you.
怎么了
Are you ok?
没关系
Nothing.
我看看
Let me see.
好了,没弄干净,好走一点
There...that's better.
我家里的事,你大概都知道了吧
D you know about my family?
知道一点
A little bit.
三个小孩,半大不小的
I have three kids
没人管,野的很
Three wild kids
都多大了
How old are they?
十岁,八岁,小的才三岁多一点
10, and 8. The yongest is 3.
河边风大,冷不冷
It's windy here. Are you cold?
都几点了
Don't you know the time?
每天打牌,都是这么晚才回来
You come home late
everytime you play cards.
干什么?你有完没完
Leave me alone.
打一次牌,你嗦一次
You gripe every time I play.
我吃你的,喝你的
Do you think you can control me
叫你管定了,是不是
because you support my living?
小声点
Lower your voice
我怕谁啊
Who should I be afraid of?
你老大,当然谁也不怕
You are the boss,
ofcourse you are afraid of no one
不要
I don't want to
你什么时候要过
When did you ever want to?
桂美约会回来,怎么说
Kuei-mei had a date today,
what did she say?
给人家续弦我就是不赞成
I don't want her to marry a widower
你不赞成,你想留着当小老婆啊
You don't want her to marry or you
want to keen her as a concubine?
你那点薪水能够养她一辈子啊！
Your salary will keep her for a lifetime!
你！你怎么这么说话
You! Why do you talk like that?
那要怎么说
How to say that
别当我不知道你那一点心眼
When I don't know your mind
上次托人从P-X弄了两瓶旁氏
Last time you got 2 bottles of
Ponds from the PX.
你不是背着我塞给她一瓶
You gave her one behind my back.
当我不知道
You think I don't know.
你！不跟你说了
You...l don't want to talk with you
请问侯永年家在哪里
Excuse me, where's
Hou Yung-Nien's home?
在那边
There.
谢谢
Thanks.
弟弟,侯永年家在哪里
Kid, where's Hou Yungnien's home?
在那边
There.
谢谢
Thanks.
有人在家吗?
Anyone home?
爸,有人找你
Dad, someone is looking for you.
谁啊
Who is it?
乖
Good kid.
出去,出去,出去啊
Get out...
坐,坐
Have a seat.
你叫什么名字?
What is your name?
我今天来是有事要跟你说清楚
I'm here to make things clear.
你说！你说...
Go ahead...
在老家的时候,我订过婚
I was engaged when I was in hometown.
这我知道,听柴太太说过
I know, Mrs. Chai told me.
我想...如杲你要我
If you want to marry me
我就不想瞒你什么
I don't want to hide anything
我十九岁在乡下订婚
I was engaged at 19 in the country side.
费家住对门,他对我很好
The Feis lived opposite to us,
he was very good to me.
后来逃难
Then we ran from the war.
说好了我跟表姐一艘船先来台湾
My cousin and I came
took a boat to Taiwan first
谁知道
Who knows...
我不想瞒你
I don't want to hide it from you.
我已经跟过他了,不是头一次
I was with him...it isn't my first time.
如果你不愿意,那就不要再提了
If you don't want me,
we can stop seeing each other
新娘来给你们敬酒了
Here come the brides
新郎,新娘敬酒来了
The couple come for a toast.
我们要跟他们干杯
Buttons up.
恭喜,恭喜
Congratulations...
谢谢各位
Thank you, cheers.
来！来！来叫妈妈,叫啊！快点
Come meet your mother, hurry...
新郎官,今天是你大喜的日子
Today is the happiest day in your life.
我们至少要干它三大杯
You must drink a least 3 glasses.
叫妈妈
Say mommy.
大声一点
Louden
妈妈
Mommy.
正兴,走
Cheng-hsing, let's go.
快吃饭了,你们去哪里啊
It's time for lunch, where are you giong?
去柴妈妈家
To Momma Chai's home.
这个时候去人家家干什么
Don't go at this time.
不要出去了,来！正兴
Stay home...Cheng-hsing!
你凭什么管我们
Why should we listen to you?
你又不是我妈妈
You are not my mother!
正全
Cheng-chuan!
你是侯大嫂吧！
Are you Mrs. Hou?
老侯结婚的时候我见过你一次
I saw you at the wedding.
他在里面
He's inside.
谢谢
Thank you.
最里边那一间
He's in the last room.
没事,没事,我老婆
It's ok...it's my wife.
没事,没事
It's 0k...
你怎么来了
Why are you here?
下雨,给你送伞来
I brought you an umbrella, it's raining.
老侯,正好给嫂子带回去
Hou, have your wife take this home.
干干净净的
It's clean.
刚上桌还没动几下,就端下来了
They hardly touched it.
谢啦！
Thanks!
鲍鱼,回去正好宵夜
Abalone, great for a midnight snack.
来,拿着
Here, take it.
谢谢
Thank you.
回来了
You are back.
给你的
This is for you.
什么啊?
What is it?
打开来看看
Open and see it.
蜜枣啊！
Honeyed jujubes.
来台湾还没见过呢！
I never saw any in Taiwan!
台湾根本没有嘛！
You can't find jujubes in Taiwan.
老赵小舅子跑船
Chads brother-in-law is a sailor.
从香港带回来的
He imported the jujubes from Hong Kong
很贵吧?
It must be very expensive.
刚好赢两把
I won a little money.
你上班赌钱,不太好吧
I don't think is right to gamble at work.
反正没有人看到嘛！吃啊
Nobody is watching! Try it!
留着明天大家一块吃吧,
Let's eat it together tomorrow.
带回来的菜呢?拿出来下酒吧
I want to eat the dish you took back.
来
Here.
带回来的菜呢
Where's the dish?
菜,我扔了
I threw it.
扔了,好好的,干干净净的怎么扔了呢
You threw it? Why?
你高尚,嫌脏,不吃剩菜
You think it's dirty?
有志气,有志气就不要嫁给端盘子的
You should not married a waiter.
我们是看人脸色,吃人剩菜惯了
Waiters are always at diposal
and are used to eat leftover.
你他妈的高尚
Fuck your diginity.
睡着啦
Are you asleep?
睡着了
Yes.
我真的没有那个意思
I don't mean it.
我怎么会嫌你呢
How could I look down on you?
跟了你,这一辈子就跟了你了
I married you, and I will be with you forever.
我只是觉得我们还能吃自己的
I just think we should eat our own food.
就不要别人剩的
We don't need leftovers from others.
你在饭店给人家做事
You work in a restaurant as a waiter now.
我都相信只要我们有志气
But I believe if we have the will.
总有一天我们会有自己的店
We can have our own restaurant some day.
就算再小的店,也都是自己的
A small restaurant will be good, too.
你先听我说完,你先听我说
Listen to me...listen to me.
你说,你说
Tell me...tell me...
还有你赌钱不好,到处欠钱
You gamble too much,
and you owed too much money.
答应我,以后不再赌
Promise me you won't gamble again.
不赌,不赌,以后不赌了
I won't, I won't gamble again.
再赌我是狗
lam adog ifldo.
关灯
Turn off the light.
爸爸
Daddy.
怎么那么早回来
Why are you back so early?
要过年了,我们也该腌几斤腊肉
We should made some cured meat
for Chinese New Year.
过年,还过个屁年啊
New Year? Who cares about New Year?
老子不干了
I quit.
妈的,受够了那王八蛋洋鬼子的气
I have had enough
from the damned foreigner.
不干了
I quit!
跟老侯说过,他这样子是不行的了
I told Hou he is heading to trouble.
不听
He didn't listen
下午几个人又躲在小房间里面打嗦哈
They hid away and played cards again
当场给撞见
and were caught at the scene.
说开除就开除了,没有第二句话
They were fired right away.
那就不能找人去说一说吗?
Could somebody help?
说什么?洋鬼子是不讲人情的
How? Foreigners are strict.
再见
Goodbye.
桂美啊
Kuei-mei.
桂美啊,过年快到了,来,留着用嘛
Keep it for Chinese New Year.
不用了,不用
No. Thanks.
这是我从家里带出来最后一些东西
This is the last think I took from home.
本来是留着生孩子用的
I planed to keep it for our baby.
先拿着把赌债还了
Sell it to pay your debts.
生孩子,到时再想办法吧
We'll find other way out
when the baby is borned.
我求求你,不要再赌了
Please, don't gamble anymore.
你要再赌,这个家就给你毁了
Or you will destroy our family.
你们不要
Don't...
我哪一次心里想的不是要多赢一点
I want to win.
好多给你们置点好东西啊
I want to buy something good for you.
看到你开心,看到孩子高兴
You don't know how happy I will be,
你不知道我心里有多舒服
just 0t see you smile.
可是我,我没办法,我没想到我这每一次
But I can't. Every time...
你以为今天这个家落到这个地步
You think I don't care about our family,
我就不关心嘛
don't you?
我知道
I know.
让我看一看
Let me see.
这么大,怎么进去的
So big. How did baby get in?
问你啊
You tell me!
利息三分先扣
I need to take 3% of interests first.
我知道,要不是为了生孩子
I know, if it weren't for the baby...
说实在的,真背不起
Honestly, I really can't bear it.
来,在这边,你拿不到
I got it. You can't take it from me.
吃饭了
Time to eat.
什么东西啊
What's that?
拿来给我,给我
Give it to me, give it to me.
给我
NOW!
小时候就爱玩这种东西,长大就会赌钱
Do you want to be a gambler in future?
不学好,不学好,不学好
Shame on you...
爸爸呢
Where's daddy?
去陈家了
He went to the Chen's.
正全,有没有看到我皮包里的钱
Cheng-chuan.
Did you see the money in my purse?
没有啊
No.
谁啊
Who is it?
开门
Open the door.
谁嘛
Who is it?
我,开门,开门
It's me. Open the door!
谁
Who is it?
把钱还我
Give me my money.
你怎么来了
Why are you here?
把钱还我
Give me my money.
什么钱嘛
What money?
我生孩子的钱
Money for my baby.
跟小皮包里的钱
The money I put in my purse.
谁拿你什么钱了,你这
What are you talking about?
我跟,加二十,看牌
I See you. Raise 20. Show cards.
把钱还我
Give my money back to me!
老侯,算了,算了,回去吧
Hou, you'd better go home.
算了什么,你们这
Come on.
我正一手同花大顺,看牌了
Now I've got a flush!
还我！
你疯了
Give me my money.
- You are crazy!
不然我杀了你
Or I Will kill you!
还我
Give my money back to me!
他妈的
Shit.
羊水破了,快生了,快！快！快！
Her water breaks.
She's having a baby! Hury!
慢点！慢点！不动,不动,
Hold on...careful...
不要怕,不要怕
Don't worry...
英国女王要生孩子了
The Queen of Enlgand is having a baby.
皇后奶奶要生孩子了
The Queen is having a baby.
痛完就好了
It'll be OK after the pain.
快点啦
Hurry.
这双胞胎一男一女,还真好玩耶
A boy and a girl, how nice!
该要吃了吧
They should eat
一次生两个,什么都得准备双份够瞧的
We have to prepare everything in double
表姐夫呢
Where's your husband?
在外面呢
Outside.
他呀,毛病多
He's got a lot of problems.
说什么女人生孩子,他不方便进来
He said he better stay outside
我去陪陪他
I'll keep him company.
不赌了吧
Does he still gamble?
再赌,一家人都不要活了
If he does, our family will be done.
还没找到事
Did he find a job?
说外头不景气,事情难找
He said the economy is bad,
and it is hard to find one.
有时想想,真恨
Sometimes I hate it.
恨不得不要跟他过了
I wish I could leave him.
女人啊,就是划不来
It's our fate.
跟了什么样的男人都得认了
We have to stay with whoever we marry.
早知道,你还不如不嫁呢
It would be better not to get married!
以前对面,那个老处女吴阿姐啊
Our neighbor MissWu, the old pinster
她现在在公馆里做阿妈
ls working as a servent
有吃有住,还有钱赚
She gets food to eat,
room to stay and money to earn.
一个人过得舒服得很呢
She's happy-
她不用像我们,整天受他们男人的气
She doesn't have to take care
of a man like we do
爸
Dad
爸爸
Daddy.
正芳啊
Cheng-fang.
正芳一向最懂事了
You are my smartest child
爸爸这一年多年来,情况实在是不大好
Daddy hasn't done well this year
今天下午听赵伯伯提起啊
This afternoon, Uncle Chao said...
他说,可以把你介绍到一家牙科医院去
He could introduce you
to work in a dental clinic.
管吃管住,还有薪水
You can eat and live there, and get paid...
你疯了
Are you crazy?
她书念得好好的
She should study in school.
你让她去做下女
And you want her to be a maid?
说这个干什么
$0?
你当我愿意啊
You think I like the idea?
我每天出去给人家磕头作揖,低声下气的
I tried hard to find a job
你当我存心找不到事啊
You think I plan to be jobless?
你要再继续赌,找到再好的事情也没用
A job won't help if you keep gambling.
你又说这个
There you start again.
你最近什么时候看我去赌过了呢
Did you see me gamble recently?
怎么没有,昨天才去打牌
Din't you? You played cards yesterday.
好！你们都怪我
Ok. It's my fault.
都怪我好了
Just put the blame on me.
你要她去念书,是不是
You want her to stay in school?
那你赚钱给她念
Then you Pay-
有人在家吗?
Anybody home?
你爸爸在不在啊
Is your faterh home?
不在,爸爸没回来
No. He is not home.
不在,我来过八趟了,全不在啊
He's not? I've been here 8 times.
He's never at home.
也真巧啊,你爸爸也真能出门啊
What a coincident!
Your father always stays out.
操,也不过是几百块钱米钱嘛
Damn! It's only a
few hundred dollars rice bill.
不要叫大家街坊邻居不好看嘛
Don't disgrace yourself in the neighborhood.
我们也是做小本生意的
We are doing a small business.
这不赚钱没关系
I don't mind not making money.
总不能连本钱都赔进去了吧
But I can't lose my capital.
一回不在,二回不在
He is never at home
我送来的米
也不知道给哪个王八蛋给吃了
Then which bastard eat the rice?
操你妈的
Fuck you.
不要你管,做下女最好
Leave me alone. It's better to be a maid.
每次不绐人家钱缴补习费
He never pay for my cramm school.
不去上学最好
I don't want to go to school.
我看啊,大概就是这一家了
It must be this one.
公馆最近是需要用人啦
The family is hiring servants recently
先生要去日本
The husband is heading to Japan.
那太太说呢,要找一对夫妻跟着去帮忙
The wife wants a couple to help.
有家有眷的也比较牢靠些
People with family are more reliable.
是要去日本啊
Giong to Japan?
是啊,看桂美愿不愿意了
Yes. It depends on Kuei-mei's decision.
多考虑考虑哦
Think about it.
去日本可不是到高雄,想回来就回来
Japan is far away.
You can't travel back and forth easily.
是要去日本耶
We are talking about Japan.
你觉得怎么样
What do you think?
我不知道
I don't know
而且,还可以带两个孩子哦
Besides, you can take two children, too.
可是,吴阿姐我有五个孩子
But I have 5 kids.
人家还管你一家呢
They don't care about your whole family.
是啊！准带两个孩子已经很不错了
Right. Allowing you to bring
2 children is generous enough.
通常给人做事,哪有准带孩子的
Usually maids can't bring kids to work.
这是特别给你们方便
This is a special deal for you.
不错嘛！赚美金耶
It's great! You will earn US dollars!
而且到了日本啊
When you arrive Japan,
侯永年就没有地方去赌了
your husband will have no place to gamble.
日本
Japan?
我三叔就是让日本人
My uncle was killed by Japanese
进南京城的时候给杀掉的
when he was in Nanjing City.
到最后,连尸首都找不到
We coudn't even find his body.
你要我到日本去,想都别想
You want me to move to Japan? No way.
我也不想去啊
I don't want to go, too.
可是,我还想让这个家以后有好日子过
But I want our family to have a better life.
再说我们去日本,帮的也是中国人
And we'll be working for
Chinese not Japanese.
你不想去,也可以
If you don't want to go, it's fine.
那你就告诉我
But tell me.
你什么时候能找到事情
When will you find a job?
你什么时候让正芳继续念书
When will you put Cheng-fang
back to school?
什么时候能把赌债全部还清
When will you pay off your gambling debts?
不然我们这个家就没有了
Our family is breaking apart.
你看人家都有钱成这个样子
Some people get all the money.
我们就是穷命啊
We were born to be poor.
走吧
Let's go.
太太
Madam.
这就是桂美跟老侯
This is Kuei-mei and Hou.
好
Good.
都说清楚了
Did you explain the rules to them?
说清楚了
Yes.
说清楚就好
Fine.
我走了
是
I am leaving
- Yes, mam.
留他们,吃饭
Keep them for dinner.
好了,就这样
OK. That's it.
她要留你们吃饭
She wants you to stay for dinner.
昨天晚上请客,还剩了一大堆菜呢
There's leftover from party last night.
你来说啊
You tell them.
我,我,我不会说啦
I...I can't.
你说嘛
You tell them.
我跟爸爸舍不得你们任何一个
We don't want to leave any of you.
可是人家不能负担我们一家七口
But we cannot all move to Japan.
所以,我跟爸爸想了很久
Your dad and I have thought it over.
我们决定
We decided...
正全没考上初中,带他到日本念书
Cheng-chuan didn't pass the test.
He can study in Japan.
双胞胎,正敏好生病,需要照顾
Cheng-min are sickly and need care.
正芳,你留在台北就是大姐了
Cheng-fang, you are the eldest kid here
要好好照顾两个弟弟
Take good care of your two brothers.
在表姨家要听表姨的话
Listen to Auntie
七筒啊
7 dots.
桂美,先生下午打雷话回来没有?
Kuei-mei,
did my husband call this afternoon?
没有
No.
七条
7 bamboos.
我说芸芝,你们老夫老妻的还像蜜糖似的
Yun-zi, although you married for year,
you are like newly wed.
一下午问三趟电话
You checked if he call three
times this afternoon.
我是问准他到底回不回来吃晚饭
Just wonder if he will come back for dinner.
这男人哪,还是看紧点好
You've got to keep an eye on men.
还是我们魏太太有办法
Mrs. Wei's is good at this.
把个魏先生管得是服服贴贴的哦
She keeps a tight rein on Mr. Wei.
没的事
Not at all.
你们魏先生忙,听说日本人指定要他
I heard the Japanese keep Mr. Wei busy.
要不是为了公司的事
Were it not for business.
谁会到这种半生不熟的地方来
Who'd like to move here?
要点长久打算,还是美国好
For the long term, US is better.
那么个女的摆在办公室
With that woman in your office...
你不怕别人说闲话,我还怕呢
People QOSSiP-
你最好
You should...
谁要你端进来的
Who told you to come in?
出去
Get out!
是
Yes.
又吵架了,是不是
They're fighting again
从来没看过这样做夫妻的
I never saw any couple like them
人前亲亲热热
Pretending happy in front of people
背后三天两头吵架
but fighting in the back.
所以说啊,门当户对还是有道理的耶
So a proper match is important.
像这个男的,一路上来全靠这女的家里
The husband depends own the wife's family
他怎么会有好日子过呢
How can it be easy for him?
老丈人听说是当官的
I heard his fater in-law is a high official.
当初,他就是看上这个女婿学问好
His father in-law likes him because
he is well educated
你没听说吧,男的最近想离婚耶
Have you heard? The man wants to divorce.
他大概受不了了,只是女的不肯
He can't take it anymore
but the wife doesn't agree.
其实夫妻做成这样,还有什么意思
Marriage is meangless to them.
那干脆一了百了,离婚算了嘛
They should divorce.
女的要面子死也不会肯的
The woman won't agree because
she doesn't want to lose face.
怎么,台北来的信啊
What is it? Letter from Taipei?
信上怎么说
What does it say?
说,都很好
It says everything is fine.
好什么呀
Fine?
一对双胞胎,跟着我们这个是白白胖胖
The twin who live with us is fat and healthy.
台北那个,瘦得跟干一样
The other in Taipei is thin and weak.
你表姐光顾着打牌嘛
You cousin is not taking good care of them.
说起那个女的
Speaking of the girl
到底有没有找他,你是他司机
Does the husband really has a mistress?
你说
You tell me...
不错,我是他司机啊
I'm his driver.
总不能他到哪我跟到哪吧
But I don't always stick with him
我想,这么大年纪
He's quite old
外面还会有女人
Having a mistress at this age
过干瘾,老来俏嘛
Must be a lot of fun
妈妈,哥哥打架架
Mommy, Brother fights.
乖,你先进去
Good girl, go in first.
哥哥打架架,哥哥坏坏
Brother fights, brother is bad.
怎么那么早回来
Why are you back so early?
你又打架了
You fight again?
学校里的日本人骂我清国奴
Japanese says I am Chinese slave.
什么
What?
骂我清国奴
They say I am a Chinese slave.
你不是说,如果他们再骂我清国奴的话
Din't you told me if they said that again,
我就可以揍他们吗
I can beat them?
那也不能不上课啊
But you can't leave school.
我不要念书了
I don't want to go to school.
念来念去都不会,没意思
I don't want to study any more. It's boring.
大师傅不是要介绍我去横滨学厨子吗
Didn't the Chef introduce me
to learn cooking?
我还不如去学厨子算了
I should better be a cook.
我不要念书了
I don't want to go to school.
去洗一洗脸吧
Go clean up.
待会我给你上药
I'll fix your wounds.
请
Please.
再见
Goodbye.
留级也没有关系
To repeat a year in school is fine.
要多听爸爸,妈妈的话
You should listen to your parents.
学学别的也好,要多多努力
You can learn something else,
but always work hard.
那么就再见了
Well then, bye.
好了,不要再送了,再见
Bye. I'm fine. Good bye.
你他妈的
Damn.
老师还说了些什么
What else did the teacher say?
日本话我也不太会听
I don't understand Japanese too well.
反正意思是啊,小孩不爱读书,要留级了
What she meant was, the kid flunked.
我都跟你说过了他不爱读书
I told you he doesn't like to study.
就到横滨去学厨子
He should learn cooking in Yokohama.
像我这样,有什么不好啊
Just like me, it's not that bad.
总比在这里学坏要好
It's better than to stay here and go astray.
学厨子,是你自己愿意的
You want to be a cook.
不过我们不管学哪一行
Waterever you choose,
都要学出个名堂来
You have to work had.
不要做一半就不做了,知道吗
You can't quit. Do you understand?
男孩子这样子一辈子会没出息的
If you quit easily,
you'll be a loser in your whole life.
在这里,你要听大师傅的话,知道吗
You must stand to the Master Chef.
自己要照顾自己
Take care of yourself.
麻烦您,多多照顾
Please take care of him.
哪里,应该的
Of course I will.
您请回吧
Bye.
要听大师傅的话
Be good.
进去
Go.
好香啊
Smells great!
好吃
It's delicious.
桂美,你作的牛肉饭,越做越道地了哦
You cook better and better.
你也不看看,是什么师傅教的
Don't you know who taught her?
桂美要是回台北开餐馆
If Kuei-mei opens a restaurant in Taipei,
准是独一无二的
she will succeed.
回去干么啊
Why do you want to go back?
时局那么坏,美援都停了
America stops supporting Taiwan.
It's not a good time.
美军也保不住,也要撒了
The US military will retreat soon.
能混啊,还不多混个两年
It's better to stay here for some more years.
混,像你这样三天两头就请假的
Stay here for some more years?
You take leave everv two or three davs
早晚会被老板辞掉
Sooner or later will be the boss quit
没有签证,你就得回台北哦
Without a visa, you have to go back to Taipei
笑话,只要日本警察我躲着点
Nonsense.
If I stay away from the japanese cops,
在东京我哪里都能混
I can stay anywhere in Tokyo.
没问题啦
No problem.
又吵架了
They are fighting again.
要不要吃一点
Do want something to eat?
不要,谢谢
No, thanks.
桂美
Kuei-mei!
留着你的好意
Save it.
魏振东
Wei Chen-tung.
离婚的事,下辈子再说
Divorce? Not in your life!
给我叫车
Call a car.
是
Yes.
你一天到晚看我们这样过日子
You see us fighting all the time
奇怪不奇怪
What do you think?
我们也常常吵
We fight all the time, too.
昨天,我走了以后
After I left yesterday,
先生跟你,都说了些什么
what did my husband say?
没有
Nothing.
Nothing?
怎么会没有
Are you sure?
听说,都说了老半天了
I heard that you talked for a long time.
我是可怜你们没地方去
I know you have no place to go.
不然早请走路了
Or I'd have dismissed you long time ago.
这里,我不想做了
I don't want to work here anymore.
怎么?那个女的又给你气受了啊
What happened?
The woman gave you a hard time again?
司机说,他可以介绍我们到外面餐馆打工
The driver can introduce us to
work in a restaurant.
是苦一点,可是赚钱比这里多
The work is harder but the pay is better.
再存点钱,我们就可以回去
We can save more money and go home.
自己开馆子,给自己做
We can open a restarant by ourselves.
出去,人生地不熟
Leaving...to an unfamiliar place...
反正也是中国人嘛
They are Chinese, too.
这日本人管麻将叫麻雀
The Japanese call mahjongg "sparrow".
开馆子了呢
It's a business here.
你看我干什么
Why are you starring at me?
到日本来什么时候赌过了
Have you ever seen me gamble here?
您好,我们是小王介绍来的
Hello, we are Mr. Wang's friends.
我知道,坐
I know. Have a seat.
谢谢您
Thank you.
我们没有在这里打工的签证
We don't have working-visa.
我知道,警察来的时候躲一躲
I know. Just hide when the cops come.
坐啊
Sit.
久等了
Sorry to keep you waiting.
他妈的,累得跟狗一样
Damn! I'm working like a dog.
在魏家十天,也没有在还里一天累
The work 'rs 10 mes
harder than at the Wars.
你在干嘛呢
What are you diong?
给碗拉了一个口子
I cut myself with a bowl.
我看看
Let me see.
你活该吧,日本是你要来的
It serves you right.
You wanted to come to Japan.
魏家也是你要离开的
You wanted to leave the Wei's.
老侯,警察,进去
Cops! Hou! Hide!
欢迎光临
Welcome.
我来查一下证件
Let me check your documents.
是
Sure.
妈妈,看电视
Mommy, let's watch TV.
操你妈的
Damn.
妈的
Damn it.
我看看
Let me see.
操,端了一辈子的盘子了
Fuck! I carried dishes all my life,
什么低声下气的事没干过
and done all disreputable jobs,
还真没躲过警察呢,操
but I never hid from cops! Fuck.
你跳船几年了
How long have you came here?
三年了
3 years.
不打算回去啦！
Do you plan to go home?
过一阵子想办法,把家里接出来
I want to bring my family here.
你们呢
And you?
我们把大儿子送到横滨去学厨子
We send our son to learn
to cook in Yokohama.
还没出师呢
He's still an apprentice.
我们要先回去
We'll go back before him.
回去干嘛,这里还满不错的
What for? It's good here.
工作又多,赚钱又容易
It's easy to find jobs and make money .
再好,还是别人的地方
Nomatter how good it is, it isn't our home.
我们要回去,自己开店,做生意
We want to open a restaurant in Taiwan.
生意那么好做,做垮了,多的是啊
It isn't easy, lots of people failed.
回来咯
We are back!
看,我给你找的房子不错呢！
How do you like the place?
很好
Great.
正芳,正芳长大了
Cheng-fang...you grow up.
妈妈
Mommy.
正兴
Cheng-hsing.
正芳
Cheng-fang.
来来来
Come...
都瘦的
So thin.
长大了,都不一样了
They're all different now.
请进
Welcome.
牛肉饭来了
Here's your beef with rice.
来,您的汤
Here's your soup.
汤
Your soup.
老板,来一客牛肉饭
I'd like some beef with rice.
咖哩饭
Curry.
咖哩饭,好！谢谢
Curry. OK, thanks.
牛肉饭一个,咖哩饭一个
A beef with rice and a curry.
来
Here.
到哪去?
Where are you going?
图书馆
Library.
忙成这个样子,也不晓得帮一下忙
She should help, we are busy.
要考试了,让她看书嘛
Let her go, she has a test.
以后不要让她穿那什么迷你裙
Don't let her wear the miniskirt.
光着两个大腿
She shouldn't show her legs like that.
像什么样子嘛
It's inappropriate.
好了啦,流行嘛
That's fashion.
我出去一下
I'm giong out.
这么晚,到哪去
It's late, where are you going?
跟老常去看几个老同事去
To visit some old friends with Old Chang.
不好意思嘛！
I can't say no.
说哦,你现在是老板了,连朋友都不要了
He said I can't abandon friends
去去就回来
I will come back soon.
谁啊
Who was it?
同学哥哥
A classmates' brother.
哪天请他家里来玩嘛
Invite him home next time.
不错耶
Not bad.
休息啊
Rest time?
中饭刚过,晚饭还有一会
Lunch time has passed,
there's some time to dinner
坐啊
Have a seat.
这是你的会钱,两万二
Here's your money, 22,000.
你又胖了耶
You put on weight.
这么忙,还要胖,有什么办法
And so busy, too. What can I do?
我不喝什么柠檬茶,喝茶有搁糖的啊
I don't drink lemon tea with sugar.
Who drink tea with sugar?
随饭附送的嘛
It comes with the meal.
现在的客人就喜欢这种洋调调
Customers like western style.
不然生意还没那么好做呢
It attracts customer.
我就不喜欢
I don't like it.
台北现在洋玩意是愈来愈多了
Taipei is more westernize now.
都像你们,买的什么西餐啊！咖啡的
Like you are serving western food
and coffee...
侯永年呢
Where is Hou?
出去了
He went out.
又去打牌
Playing cards again?
以前老同事,说应酬两次
Old friends said he had to go.
打牌倒是没有什么关系
There's nothing wrong to play cards.
别在外面给你弄个女人
As long as he doesn't play women.
他不会
He won't.
男人啊,有两个钱,骚得很
Men becomes wolfish
when they have money.
不一定哦
It's hard to tell.
表姐,正芳有男朋友了
Cheng-fang's got a boyfriend.
你知道吧
You know that?
没有啊,以前在我那儿没见过
No! I never saw one before.
才这么点大交什么男朋友呢
She is too young to have a boyfriend.
其实,交男朋友倒没有什么关系
There's nothing wrong to have a boyfriend.
只要正正当当就好
As long as he is a proper fellow.
你倒是很开通
You are open-minded.
出过洋,是不一样哦！
Living abroad makes you a different person.
正兴,开门
Cheng-hsnig. Open the door.
快关门
Close the door.
爸爸呢
Where is your dad?
刚才有个女人打电话来
A woman called.
叫他去打牌了
She asked him to play cards.
哪个女的
What woman?
她打来好几次,每次都是我接的耶
She called several times,
I answered the phones many times.
姐回来了
Sister is back.
我不要听,我不要听
I don't want to listen to you!
正芳
Cheng-fang.
我不要听
I don't want to listen to you!
你碰我干什么,不要拉我
Why do you touch me? Don't pull me.
不必,要说跟你妈去说
No! Tell your mom.
你不敢,对不对
You don't dare to, do you?
正芳
Cheng-fang.
吵架啦
You fight?
我是不反对你交男朋友
It's ok to have a boyfriend
可是有什么事情
But whatever happens,
也要让家里知道,好放心
you should let us know. So we won't worry.
放什么心,你们去日本那么多年什么都不管
Worry?
You left us and went to Japan for years.
现在回来管什么管
Why should you worry now?
你管你管,我看你能管什么
I'll see what you can worry about.
你不要跟我别扭
Don't be obstinate with me.
你现在还小
You are still young.
有很多事情,我当然要管
Of course I worry about you.
等你念了大学
When you get into college,
我一定不再管你,好不好
I won't worry about you anymore, ok?
正兴
Cheng-hsing...
Cheng-hsing!
正芳
Cheng-fang.
Cheng-fang!
正芳
你们听到没有
Do you hear me?
快带弟弟出来,淹水了
Bring your younger brother.
The water is coming in.
正芳
Cheng-fang!
敏敏,来
Min-min, come.
不怕,妈妈抱,来
Don't be afraid, let me hug you.
妈
Mom.
不怕,来,不怕,妈妈在
Don't be afraid, here, mom is here.
到妈妈房间去
Go to my room.
正芳,你还坐那干嘛,听到没有
Why are you still sitting there, Cheng-fang?
弟
Little brother.
不许再下来
Don't move.
妈,爸爸呢
Mom, where's dad?
水再涨
If the water keeps rising,
我们就掀了天花板上屋顶去
We go to the roof.
淹水了,真糟糕
What a mess!
昨天晚上本来要回来的
I planed to come back last night,
后来风实在是太大了
but the wind was too strong.
马路上车子一辆也叫不...
There wasn't a single taxi...
来,我来帮忙
Come, let me help...
你这是干什么嘛
What are you doing?
不是你让我到仁爱路去问房子价钱
Didn't you ask me to check the house price?
刚来台湾的时候
When we come to Taiwan,
那儿一坪二百块钱卖我
the price was $200 for 3.3 square meter.
我还不要
I didn't want it.
现在涨的跟金子一样了
Now it's more expensive.
老常说,房子反正带不走
Chang says,
you can't take a house with you.
他说让你干脆置点金子靠得住
You better buy gold.
对不起,打烊了
I'm sorry. We are closed.
请问侯永年是不是住在这里
Excuse me, does Hou live here?
你找他有什么事
How can I help you?
里边坐
Come in.
坐
Have a seat.
谢谢
Thank you.
有什么事不能跟我说吗
Is there anything that you can't tell me?
我是来问问他,他说要对我们母女好的
I'm here to ask him.
He said he will be good to us.
怎么一下子,好久也不露一下面
But I have not seen him for a long time.
难道就这样子算了吗
Is that it?
我又不是那种
I'm not that kind of...
随随便便的女人啊
loose woman.
正兴,正兴
Cheng-hsing...Cheng-hsing...
正兴到哪儿去了
Where are you?
正...
Cheng...
那个女的
The woman...
她丈夫坐牢去了
Her husband is in jail.
老常认识她,总是到她们家去打牌
I played mahjongg at her house.
就是台风那天晚上
In the typhoon night...
我本来是要回来的
I planned to come back.
可是实在走不了
But I couldn't leave.
我跟她
So we...
以后不会再有了
It won't happen again.
真的,我跟她说清楚,以后不会有了
I'll make it clear to her. Never again.
你这是在干什么嘛
What are you doing?
我不要再跟你过下去了,我要离婚
I'm leaving you. I want a divorce.
离婚,离什么婚啊你
Divorce? What do you mean by divorce?
你跟那个日本的魏太太学
You learned from Mrs. Wei in Japan?
你学什么学嘛
Why do you learn that?
我不用学别人
I don't need to learn from others.
我什么苦都能跟你吃
I can suffer a hard life with you.
女人的事,我绝不原谅你
But I will not forgive you to have an affair.
现在外头工厂多的是,饿不死的
There are plenty of jobs, I can survive.
等我安顿好
When I settle down,
五个孩子都是我的
I'll take all the kids.
我会来接的
I'll come back to pick them up.
妈
Mom.
来
Come here.
正芳离家出走了
Cheng-fang left.
她同学家都找过了
We checked with her classmate
说有个男孩子
They said she has a boyfriend.
图书馆里认识的
They met in a library.
不知道他住哪里
I don't where he lives.
自从你里开家家里乱七八糟的
Since you left, everything is a mess.
正兴也被大锅烫伤了
Cheng-hsing burned himself on a pot.
哥哥伤的重不重
Is your brother hurt badly?
现在已经没事了
He's okay now.
爸爸,你就当没有生过我
Daddy, pretend I'm not your daughter.
我走了
I'm leaving.
也许我的事会使你觉得丢脸
Maybe what I do will make you lose face.
可是我绝不后悔
But I will never regret.
你们从来不了解我
You never understand me.
以后也不会了解的
And you never will.
所以,请不要来找我
So please don't find me.
以后厨房里不准去,多危险啊
Stay away from the kitchen. It's dangerous.
是爸爸叫我去帮忙的
Dad told me to go and help out.
喂
Hello?
是
This is she.
我知道,我马上来
I see... I'll be right there.
一大早,她就说要来跟我们阿盛结婚
She came and wanted to
marry our son Ah-sheng.
原来,我以为她是开玩笑
At first I thought she was joking.
谁知道她就站在那里
But she stood there.
说什么都不走耶
And wouldn't leave.
连我们阿盛都吓得要命
We were scared.
是啦,如果真的有了小孩
Right...lf she's really pregnant,
我们也是要负责的
we would take the responsibility.
可是,侯太太
But Mrs. Hou...
你看要是要他们两个现在结婚
Look at her.
那是不可能的
It's impossible that they get married now.
因为啊,两个都还是小孩都还要读书
They are kids. They need to study.
再说啊,我们阿盛也不敢哪
Besides,
Ah-sheng wouldn't dare to marry her.
对啦,是我们阿盛不好
Right, it's Ah-sheng's fault.
这肚子里的小孩
The baby...
我们林家也是舍不得
We don't want to give up the baby.
可是,这是没有办法的耶
But we can't help.
没办法
Can't help?
坐下,没你的事情
Sit, chill out.
我看啊,大家都不要生气啦
I think we should calm down.
好好商量,想个办法
Let's find a way to solve the problem.
这个钱啊我们是不会吝啬的
We can pay for it.
林太太,正芳年纪还小
Mrs. Lin,Cheng-fang is young.
什么都不懂
She doesn't know anything.
怀孕的事,不一定是真的
She might not be pregnant.
这件事情只能怪她自己心太死
She's too ignorant
容易相信人家
and she believes people easily
今天你们的态度
If she knows what you said
她也应该死心,不会再傻了
she should give up and stops being silly.
我们会带她回去好好跟她说
We will talk to her.
今天的事情
Today...
我们就当它没发生过
We'll peretend nothing happened.
我就打死你
I'll beat you to death.
侯永年,你干什么
What are youd doing?
侯永年
Hou Yung-nien!
你打死我,你打死我好了
Come on! Beat me to death!
我不在乎,打死我好了
I don't care! Let me die!
侯永年
Hou Yung-nien!
侯永年,你给我起来
Hou Yung-nien! Stop!
怎么样
You want to kill her, don't you?
你想打死她,是不是
What is it?
怎么样,什么地方不舒服啊
Feeling unwell?
林大夫,我以前来过
Dr. Lin, I've been here before.
在这儿生过孩子
I had my babies here
侯太太啊,双胞胎的
Mrs. Hou, twins.
孩子已经很大了吧
They must be big now.
对
Yes.
快要上小学了
Going to primary school.
那
So...
我今天来
I'm here today
是有事情想麻烦您
to ask for your help.
是我女儿
It's my daughter.
她才十五岁
She's only 15.
可能,可能有了
And she...she's probably pregnant.
发生这种事情
Letting it happen,
我们做大人的也有责任
We are also responsble
不能,不能就这样毁了她一辈子
We can't destroy her life...
正芳所受的打击
No one can suffer on behalf of Cheng-fang.
没有人能代替她
No one.
但是她总是要长大的
She had to grow up.
正芳念大学那年
When Cheng-fang went to college,
我们向跟行贷款
we got a loan from the bank.
买了自己的房子,开西餐厅
Bought a house and run the restaurant.
生意还不错
The business was good.
丈夫有女人
A husband having an affair
比赌钱更叫人寒心
is worse than gambling.
可是你也只有两种选择
But you have two choices,
离开他,或者原谅他
to leave or to forgive.
我觉得两个都不好
Nether are easy.
可是总是要选一样啊
But you have to choose one.
这是正全,他娶了个日本小姐
This is Cheng-chuan,
he married a Japanese lady.
正兴念的是国际贸易
Cheng-hsing studied International Business.
这是他的公司跟他的太太
This is hisoffice and his wife.
这是双胞胎大学的时候
When the twins graduated from college,
全家的合照
we took this photo.
只可惜少了正全一家
But Cheng-chuan's family were not there.
人原来是会老的
Everybody grows old.
年轻的时候
When we were young,
就从来没有想到过
we never think about it.
而且还会生病
We not only grow old, but being ill.
女人的事
Women...
他倒是真的没有再犯过
He never cheated on me since then.
不过,偶尔还是赌的
But still, he gambles sometimes.
只是从知道我子宫是癌以后
Yet since he knew I have uterus cancer,
倒是没见他再赌过
he quit gambling.
孩子们大了
Kids have grown up.
各人有各人的事
They have their own business.
我住院以后
After I was in the hospital,
霞飞之家的生意
The restaurant
就只有正芳帮着照顾
is handled by Cheng-fang.
大家都说
Everyone says that
她愈来愈像我了
she becomes more and more like me.
你应该去接
You should pick them up
你应该去机场接一接的
from the airport
哪有老子接儿子的
No fathers will pick up their sons.
死脑经
Stubborn man.
奶奶
Grandma!
爷爷,奶奶
Grandpa! Grandma!
全来了
Everyone is here.
奶奶
Grandma!
宝宝过来
Come here, Bow-bow.
宝宝,贝贝
Bow-bow, Bei-bei.
叫爷爷,奶奶,乖哦
Say hello to your grandparents.
爸
Dad.
妈
Mom.
爷爷,奶奶
Granpa, grandma.
爸,奶奶生病了
Dad.
- Grandma is sick.
妈
Mom
妈,气色好多了耶
Mom you look better.
不要拉我
Don't pull me.
姑姑看一看
Let auntie see.
贝贝,有没有想姑姑啊
Bei-bei, do you miss me?
有哦
Yes?
玛莉子,叫奶奶
Mariko, say hello to grandma.
叫啊
Hurry
奶奶
Grandma.
在日本跟她妈都说日本话
She speaks Japanese
with her mom in Japan.
没办法
There is no way.
给爷爷看看
Let grandpa see you
爸爸
Dad.
怎么生了个日本娃娃呢
A Japanese baby, huh?
叫爷爷
Call "grandpa".
不会叫,不会叫
Can you say it?
拿东西给你吃
Take it.
不要乱跑哦,乖
Behave yourself.
贝贝想吃什么
What do you want to eat, Bei-bie?
正全,你胖了
Cheng-chuan, you gained weight.
八十五了
85 kg now.
宝宝,宝宝
Bow-bow...
吃药了没有
Did you take the pills?
吃过了
Yes.
来,我们去找奶奶
Come, let's find grandma.
拿苹果果给他们吃嘛
Give them some apples.
叫奶奶哦
Grandma.
越来越不听话
You're naughty.
随他们去吧
Let them go.
你离婚的事
About your divorce...
爸还好不高兴了一阵子
Dad is upset about it for a while.
这种事,有什么办法呢
What can I do?
你真的不打算留在台北吗
You don't want to stay in Taipei?
在外头也没有那么好混
It's not easy to make money outside.
你日本话说得再好
Even if you speak Japanese well,
他们还是当你外国人
they still see you as a foreigner.
只是,那么多年待久了惯了
But I'm used to living in Japan.
反而台北不熟
Taipei is strange place to me.
都还指望你留下来,把店接过去做
I wish you could stay and
take over the restaurant.
不太可能
It's impossible.
店里生意怎么样
How's the business?
现在竞争多
Lots of competition.
生意愈来愈难做了
It's hard to make money.
房子倒是愈来愈值钱了
But the house worth a lot.
我看经营方式是有问题
I think, the problem is the way
of running the restaurant.
那样的菜单不行了
The menu is old fashion.
装潢也太旧了
The decoration is old.
店里一直是她跟爸爸在管
Mom and dad take care of the restaurant.
我也很少过来
I seldom come here.
她病了
After she became sick,
我才辞了学校的工作过来帮忙
I quit my job at school and came.
本来,我一直打算再出去念两年书的
I planned to study abroad
for one or two years.
多大了,还念书
Study abroad? At your age?
嫁人算了
You should get married.
我不是跟你开玩笑的
I'm not joking.
除了你我还没有告诉别人
I haven't told anyone else.
正兴呢
How about Cheng-hsing?
正兴嫌累,根本做不来
He think it's too hard.
正群又想移民到美回
Chang-shun wants to move to the States.
快餐两份,柳丁汁一份
Two quick meals with orange juice.
洗手间的水箱漏成那个样子
The toilet is leaking.
怎么也不叫人修理呢
Why don't you have somebody fix it?
对不起,我不知道
I'm sorry. I don't know that.
我从来不用女厕所的
I don't use lady's room.
这是谁,谁换的唱片,关掉,关掉
Who change the music? Turn it off.
老板娘不是规定过吗
Didn't Mrs. Hou set the rules?
不准放唱歌的音乐
Music with singing is not permitted.
你们怎么搞的,你们这
What...What's wrong with you?
小妹,你来,你来看看,你来
Here...Come over here. Look.
这还像个什么店
What kind of place is this?
老板娘一不在
As soon as Mrs. Hou leaves,
你们就把这当当成狗窝了
you mess up the place.
不要这样做事嘛
Don't you have self-respect?
你进去吧,正全在里面
Go in. Cheng-chuan's there.
不要总在这里骂人
Don't scold here.
现在小妹不好请
It's hard to find one these days.
不好请怎么样,不好请我们自己做嘛
So what? We can do the work ourselves!
好了,好了
Fine, fine.
乱七八糟的,什么东西
What a mess...
正兴呢
Where's Cheng-hsing?
他啊,忙得很,每天进进出出
He's busy in and out.
就是没看见多赚点钱回来
But he earn little.
大姐,我找你商量一点事
Sis, there's something
I want to discuss with you.
什么事啊
What is it?
我看上忠孝东路一个店
I found a place at Zhongxiao Eset Rd.
想搞个委托行
I want to open a consignment store.
如果,霞飞之家收掉
If we close the Chavannes,
咱们两个合伙
we can work together...
谁说霞飞之家要收掉
Who said we will close the restaurant?
不收掉谁做啊
Who will take care of the place then?
正全不是也要回日本去吗
Isn't Cheng-chuan returning to Japan?
再说,最近生意又不怎么样
Business is not well recently.
正兴说,还是收掉的好
Cheng-hsing says it should be closed.
霞飞之家要不要收掉,爸爸会决定
Only dad can make such decision.
用不着我们操心
It's not our business.
委托行的事,我也不懂这些
I know nothing about consignment.
为什么不找正敏呢
Why don't you ask Cheng-min?
正敏,我才懒得招惹她呢
Cheng-min? I don't want to bother her.
到底不一样啊
It isn't the same, you know.
有什么不一样
What the differences?
当然不一样
Of course it's different.
你妈对你们,跟对双胞胎就是不一样
Mom treats you and the twins diffrerently.
我不觉得有什么不一样
I don't think there are any differences.
你们吃吧
Go on and eat.
快吃啊你
Stop playing-
昨天不是说想吃柳丁吗
Didn't you say you wanted oranges?
夏天都是冷冻的,不太好
In summer, there are only frozen organes.
贵不贵
Is it expensive?
放心,没有水蜜桃贵
Less expensive than peaches .
你啊,就是小气
You're stingy.
我是没有你们大方
I'm not as generous as you are.
一套衣服八千块
Spending 8000NTD for a dress.
日本进口的耶,当然贵啦
It's imported from Japan.
It's expensive of course.
我就不晓得好在哪里
I don't know why it is good.
妈,他来了,我要走了
Mom. He's here. I'm leaving.
还有晚上要帮我留六个位子哦
Save six seats for me tonight.
我要请朋友吃饭,拜拜
Where's dad?
爸呢
I'm treating my friends. See you.
说去买什么补药
Said he was giong to buy some tonic.
随他了
Whatever.
放着,等一下
Leaveit
正全要回日本跟你说了吧
Did Cheng-chuan tell you he was leaving?
正兴,正群,也都有自己的打算
Cheng-hsing and Cheng-chun
have their own plans.
正芳,如果你也不愿意
Cheng-fang, if you don't want the restaurant,
我会慢慢地劝劝你们爸爸
I'll try to persuade your father...
让他把店卖了
To sell the place...
他一定不肯的
I know he won't agree.
只有好好跟他说了
I'll tell him nicely.
我来说
I'll do it.
真想出去走一走
I'd like to go out for a walk.
哪天问问大夫
When the doctor says you can go,
我借正兴的车,一起出去走走
I'll borrow Cheng-hsing's car for us.
你们妈妈留了点首饰
Your mom left some jewelry.
说正全过两天就得要走了
She said Cheng-chuan is about to leave.
让我先拿出来给你们
So she wanted me to give it to you.
她说啊,只是纪念品
She said it's just souvernirs.
她也搞不清楚公平不公平了
She doensn't know if it's fair or not.
她这一辈子惦记着的就是要对你们公平
She wanted to be fair to you all her life.
辛苦了一辈子
She had a hard time.
想要对她好一点,来不及了
It's too late to be good to her now.
好了,就这样了
OK. That's it!
正敏马上就是人家的人了
Cheng-min will soon get married.
店里头有正芳
Cheng-fang is handling the restaurant.
好
OK.
那以后你们有空回来看看嘛
Come back to visit when you have time.
行了,好了
OK. That's all.
爸,大姐总是要嫁人的啊
Dad, Cheng-fang will get
married sooner or later.
爸一个人顾店太累了
Dad can't handle the
restaurant all by himself.
霞飞之家该考虑卖了
You should sell the restaurant.
卖了,为什么要卖了
Sell it? Why?
爸,店卖掉了你也可以轻松一下
Dad, you can relax if it's sold.
我很好,我不要轻松,你们,你这
I'm fine. I don't want to relax.
霞飞之家是我跟你妈辛辛苦苦一辈子
Your mom and I worked hard for the place.
我不要卖,一辈子不卖
I won't sell it, never!
只要我还在
As long as I am alive,
你们谁也不准再跟我提起这个事情
don't you ever mention this again.
正群,正敏在这里生的吗?
Were Cheng-chun
and Cheng-min born here?
恩
Yes.
这几年,我一直在想
I've been thinking these years.
当初也许不该去日本的
Maybe we shouldn't have gone to Japan.
放下你们没人管
And left you alone.
害你,一定一直心里不舒服吧?
You must felt awful.
那么多年了也没什么不舒坦的
I feel okay now.
倒是,你那时候真的不怪爸爸了吗
But did you really forgive dad that time?
女人的事啊
About the affair?
反正,夫妻嘛,总有一个要忍啊
We're couple. One of us has to be tolerant.
为什么忍的总是女人呢
Why are always women being tolerant?
所以,你一直不想结婚
Is that why you don't want to get married?
我总觉得你不该那么容忍爸爸的
I think you shouldn't have forgiven dad.
也许你对
Maybe you're right.
不过,你总不会叫我现在离婚吧
But you wouldn't want us to divorce now.
就是你那个开餐厅的有钱的表妹啊?
It that the rich cousin
who open the restaurant?
不是得了癌症吗,怎么还能来
I thought she has a cancer,
how can she come?
小声点,好不好
Lower your voice
走了,走了,晚上吃过晚饭
Let's go. After dinner.
过来接着打西风啊,别忘了
Come and continue the game. Don't forget.
知道了,知道了
OK.
小凤,小凤啊,绐你表姨,表妹倒茶
Hsiao-feng, make some tea
for your auntie and cousin.
表姨
Auntie.
正芳
Cheng-fang.
坐,坐嘛
Have a seat.
来
Here.
谢谢表嫂
Thank you.
正芳,还记得柴妈妈吗
Cheng-fang,
do you remember Momma Chai?
柴妈妈
Momma Chai.
从前总去柴妈妈家,喝教堂牛奶的
You always went to Chai's house,
and drank milk at church.
在路上看见了都已经不认识了
I wouldn't recognize her now.
柴太太上个月搬到对门来了
Mrs. Chai moved to next door last month.
你说巧不巧啊
Isn't it a coincidence?
桂美啊,你胖多了
Kuei-mei, you've put on a lot of weight.
你看你表姐啊愈来愈瘦了
Your cousin is getting thinner and thinner.
她身体不好
Her health is not good
还一天到晚打牌嘛
but she still plays mahjongg.
不打牌干什么呢
Or what else should I do?
整天闷在这个鬼国民住宅里头
I'm cooped in this damn house.
像鸽子笼一样啊
Like a bird in the cage.
我不像你还有个生意弄弄
Unlike you, you have a business to do.
尤其是你表姐夫过世之后
After my husband passed away...
我更是连个吵架的人都没有呢
I don't even have anybody to fight with.
听起来,你很爱吵啊
It sounds like you love to fight.
那就让你每天跟我老柴去吵
Then you can argue with my husband everyday.
看你受不受得了
Let's see if you can handle it.
你不知道啊
Know what?
老柴大陆上的太太从香港出来了
Chai's Chinese wife came from Hong Kong.
柴太太吃了这么多年的苦
After so many hard years,
她心里当然不高兴了
of couse she is not happy.
我不是不高兴,我就是生气
I'm not unhappy, I'm furious.
当初他骗我,他还没结婚
He told me he wasn't married.
后来多一个太太
But now there's another wife.
每个月还要寄钱给她
He sent her money every month.
还寄电视,录音机,没完没了
He also sent her TV, radio, and other stuff.
那怎么办呢
What could you do about it?
我还能怎么办
What could I do?
苦也苦过了,孩子也把他带大了
I suffered. The kids have grown up.
高兴的时候,我就算了
When I feel good, I forgive him.
不高兴的时候,我就跟他吵架
When I feel bad, I fight with him.
到底是三十年的夫妻了,对不对
You've married for 30 years, right?
老都老了嘛,还能怎么样
You're old now. What can you do?
桂美,我忘了告诉你一件事
Kuei-mei,
there's something I forget to tell you.
我托老柴啊,在香港的太太
I asked Chai to have his Hong Kong wife
帮我们回去,打听老家的事情
check the situation of our hometown.
你啊,再也想不到,谁转来了一件东西呢
You'll never guess who sent us a package.
你看
Look.
费振邦,你以前的未婚夫耶
Fei Chen-pang. Your former fiance!
是不是他
Is it him?
没有信,有些话不方便
There's no letter. It's inconvenient to tell everything.
说,知道你很好,他很高兴
He said he's happy to know you are well here.
他有两个女儿,希望能绐弄出来
He has 2 daughters and
hope to send them out.
想跟你商量一件事
I want to discuss with you.
霞飞之家我想整修一下
I'd like to renovate the Chavannes.
换个经营方式,再重新做做看
And change the manage way.
这样很好,我可以放心了
That's good. I can count on you.
费家的事,托给你了
I'll leave the matter of the Fei's to you.
多照顾你爸爸
Take care of your dad.
没事的时候,劝他打打牌
Ask him to play cards
when he has nothing to do.
年纪大了,没有别的嗜好
He's old and has no other habbit.
偶尔打打牌,也许日子会好过一点
Playing cards can make him feel better.
你累了,睡一下吧
You're tired. Go get some sleep.